-==www.RagBear.com==- 是, 首相  第1季第3集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=- 翻译: ethanzdp 校对&时间轴: tpring
烟幕重重
弗兰克 问题是 凡是新首相
Frank, the problem is all new Prime Ministers
都想削减税收 或者公共支出
want to cut either taxes or public expenditure.
谢谢 这也是哈克想干的事
Thank you. That's what Hacker wants, too.
政客就和孩子一样
Politicians are like children.
不能让他们为所欲为 否则会宠坏他们      对
give them what they want only encourages them!
但是 有一点要明确 汉弗莱
But let's be clear about this, Humphrey.
整个体制要靠你这个内阁秘书来控制首相
The entire system hinges on you as Cabinet Secretary controlling the PM
我这个财政部常任秘书控制财政大臣
and on me as Permanent Secretary at the Treasury controlling the Chancellor.
是吧?      是
Right? Right.
还要我们保持他们关系紧张 猜忌 敌对
And on both of us keeping an agreeable tension between them, mistrust, hostility.
放心吧 没有我们 他俩也不会太热乎
Mind you, I think they'd manage that all right even without us.
财政大臣永不会原谅首相打败他进入了10号
The Chancellor will never forgive the Prime Minister for beating him to Number 10
而首相 他永远也不会相信财政大臣
and the Prime Minister will never trust the Chancellor.
毕竟 你不能信任你骗过的人     也许不能
One never trusts anyone one has deceived. Perhaps not.
减税能让他们齐心协力 会给他俩都赢得选票
But tax cuts unite them. They get them both votes.
对 可是弗兰克 这次减税得靠首相幻想的
Yes, but surely this tax cut is contingent upon the Prime Minister's fantasy
取消三叉戟 重振陆军的计划吧
about cancelling Trident and switching to conventional forces.
反正 他想拱手让出15亿我们的钱
Nevertheless, he is giving away ?.5 billion of our money!
不可想象 提案也不行
It's unthinkable, even if only proposals.
我费了好大劲说服财政大臣反对它
I had a real job getting the Chancellor to oppose it.
你怎么做的?
How did you do it?
我说我们需要钱资助医院 学校和老人
I used the one about our needing the money for hospitals, schools and old people.
人工肾战术     对 "人道主义大臣"
The kidney machine gambit. The caring Chancellor (!)
就是这个办法     是啊 这招是管用
Yes, that one. It usually works.
可是弗兰克 减点税不用这么小题大做吧?
But would a tax cut matter all that much?
只是15亿而已
It's only ?.5 billion.
对 钱是不多 我是担心你居然让它轻易通过了
I agree, it's not much in itself. My worry is about you letting it get through so soon.
如果我是你们财政部秘书
If I were in your shoes at the Treasury,
我会更担心现在的经济状况 低生产力
I'd be much more worried about the state of the economy, low productivity.
这可不是我们的错
That's not our fault.
都怪英国工人 好吃懒做 就想天上掉馅饼
It's the British worker fundamentally lazy, wants something for nothing.
旷工时数越来越多
The figures for absenteeism are going up and up.
没人肯老实工作一天
Nobody wants to do an honest day's work.
真惊人 总之 我得走了     下午很忙?
Shocking! I must rush. Busy afternoon?
是啊 我听说英格兰是3比70
Yes, indeed. I gather England are 70 for 3.
喔 喔 慢点 杰拉德
Whoa, whoa! Easy does it, Gerald.
这种酒多得是      干杯 敬公务员系统
Plenty more where that came from. Cheers. To the Civil Service!
敬英国的烟草集团及其主席
To the British Tobacco Group and its chairman.
谢谢
Thank you.
一下午板球真惬意啊
I do love a good afternoon's cricket.
知道吗 你们烟草集团的人都是国家的恩人
You know, you chaps at BTG are national benefactors really.
您这么想 我真的非常荣幸
We like to think so.
杰拉德 我想请你帮个忙 给皇家歌剧院
You know, Gerald, I've got a small favour to ask on behalf of the Royal Opera House.
你知道 伦敦剧院区差不多是为内阁运营的
Now, as you know, Covent Garden is more or less run from the Cabinet Office.
但我听说 明年有些剧目要难产了 资金不足
But I'm told that one or more productions are threatened next year, lack of funds.
今天下午我请了体育大臣来
Well, I've got the Minister for Sport coming along this afternoon.
我知道他想拉我支援温布尔登
I know he wants to twist my arm on behalf of Wimbledon
布兰兹哈奇赛车之类的
or Brands Hatch or something.
伦敦剧院区...我们想想办法
Covent Garden... We'll see what we can do.
哦 要是没有你 我们都该怎么办呢?
Oh, I don't know where we'd all be without you.
告诉我 你请了彼得索恩吗?
Tell me, have you ever invited Peter Thorne?
卫生大臣?      是 你总得顾及他的
The Minister of Health? You always included them.
他来不了 被禁烟游说团拉去了
This one's been got at by the anti-smoking lobby.
哦 多愚蠢的人啊
Oh, silly man!
非常蠢 他在政府里影响不大吧?
Very silly. He hasn't got much clout in Whitehall, has he?
无足轻重 他只是个大臣嘛
None at all. He's just a minister.
好球
Good shot!
他出局了?
Was he out?
汉弗莱 这份报告上说 如果以征兵取代三叉戟
Humphrey, this paper says that if we cancel Trident and bring in conscription,
我们可以减税15亿 可你猜我发现什么?
we shall have ?.5 billion for tax cuts, and what do I find?
您发现什么 首相?     我发现财政大臣竟然反对
What do you find, Prime Minister? The Chancellor opposes me.
这是多好的挣选票机会 他却不要 你不惊讶吗?
A great chance to be popular with the voters and he says no. Doesn't that surprise you?
不惊讶
No.
我倒是吃了一惊 你怎么这么平静?
Why doesn't it surprise you?
他听财政部的 他们吃进的钱可不会吐出来
He's advised by the Treasury and they don't believe in giving money back.
又不是他们的 是纳税人的钱
It's not theirs. It's the taxpayers'.
是有这么一说 可财政部不同意
That's not the view the Treasury takes.
只要钱入了他们掌控     可如果他们不需要
Not once they've got it. But if they don't need it?
什么?     如果他们不需要
Sorry? If they don't need it.
税收和需求无关     那和什么有关?
Taxation isn't about what you need. What is it about?
首相 财政部不会先想好怎么花 再设法敛财
The Treasury doesn't work out what they need and then think how to raise the money.
那他们怎么做?
What DOES it do?
只要可能 敛得越多越好 然后再找地方花
They pitch for as much as they can get away with, then think what to spend it on.
如果因为不需要 就把钱还回去
If you start giving money back because you don't need it,
您就破坏了几个世纪的老规矩
you're breaking with centuries of tradition.
比如 英国海军会怎么样?
What would happen to the British Navy?
照旧 我们需要海军嘛
We still need a navy.
我们只有4艘大型军舰 所以只需4个海军上将
We have four capital ships, so we need only four admirals
和1个元帅就够了
and one Admiral of the Fleet.
现在有多少上将?     60个
How many Admirals have we got? 60.
财政部是最有权势的部 因为它控制所有的钱
The Treasury's the most powerful department as it controls all the money.
夺走它的钱 等于夺走它的权 他们自然要反抗
If you take away its money, you take away its power, so they resist.
那怎样让财政部同意减税?     让财政大臣同意
How will the Treasury agree to tax cuts? Get the Chancellor to agree.
怎样才能让大臣同意呢?     让财政部同意
How will the Chancellor agree? Get the Treasury to agree.
汉弗莱 这不可能     对 首相 这本来就不可能
This is impossible. Yes, Prime Minister, it is impossible.
一定有办法逼财政部出手     有啊 逼大臣出手
We must be able to force the Treasury's hand. Yes, by forcing the Chancellor's hand.
怎么逼大臣出手呢?     逼财政部出手
How do I force the Chancellor's hand? By forcing the Treasury's hand.
汉弗莱      首相 您不能说服财政大臣吗?
Can't YOU persuade the Chancellor?
他毕竟是您的内阁成员
He's your Cabinet colleague.
关键就在这里 我需要有个自己人帮忙
That's the point. I need help from somebody who's on my side.
首相 卫生部大臣来了
The Minister of State at the DHSS is here.
让他进来 谢谢 汉弗莱      谢谢 首相
Show him in. Thank you, Humphrey. Thank you, Prime Minister.
索恩博士 首相      彼得 快进来
Dr Thorne, Prime Minister. Peter, come in.
请坐
Sit down.
你想跟我讨论...?
Now, you wanted to talk to me about...?
香烟     哦 对对
Cigarettes. Ah, yes.
您看我的报告了吧?     那是当然
You read my paper? Yes, absolutely.
您作何感想?
How did you react?
好的 你能否用自己的话总结一下呢?
Well, I...wonder if you could summarise it in your own words.
这就是我自己的话
Those WERE my own words.
是 当然 当然
Yes, yes, exactly, of course.
但首相一向认为 摘要可以明确要点 概括重点
But the Prime Minister often finds that a brief summary focuses on the salient points.
重点 没错
Salient points, precisely.
好 简而言之 我提议政府采取行动来禁烟
Well, briefly, I'm proposing that the government should take action to eliminate smoking,
彻底封杀对烟草的赞助和广告 甚至销售
a complete ban on all cigarette sponsorship and advertising,
投入5千万宣传禁烟政策
?0 million to be spent on anti-smoking publicity,
所有公共场所禁烟 未来5年内提高烟草累进税
a ban on smoking in all public places and progressive tax rises over the next five years
直到一包20根的烟和一瓶威士忌一样贵
until a packet of 20 costs about the same as a bottle of whisky.
这是不是太猛了点?
Isn't that rather drastic?
当然 这样能减少80%吸烟率
Absolutely. It should reduce smoking by at least 80%
走运的话能减少90%
90% if we're lucky
能让所有烟草公司破产
and drive tobacco companies out of business.
当然 彼得 你知道基本上我是支持你的
Yes. Well, Peter, of course, you know I agree with you basically.
吸烟理应被禁止
Smoking should be stopped.
毫无疑问 我们终归要完成这项任务
No question. And we will stop it in due course.
等时机成熟 万事俱备
At the appropriate juncture, in the fullness of time.
您是说算了?     当然不是
You mean forget it? No, absolutely not.
但我们得现实些 你我都不是昨天刚出生
But we must be realists. You and I weren't born yesterday.
对 也不是昨天刚死掉      什么?
No, and we didn't die yesterday. No. What?
每天有300人因吸烟英年早逝
300 people did prematurely as a result of smoking.
每年至少10万人死亡
100,000 deaths a year at least.
的确吓人 但你知道内阁会怎么说
It's appalling, but you know
财政部会怎么说?
what the Treasury would say?
对 他们会说烟草每年带来40亿税收 至关重要
They'd say that smoking brings in ? billion a year in revenue.
你斗不过财务部的      对 从财政方面而言
You can't beat the Treasury. Not with financial arguments.
但这是个道德问题
But this is a moral argument.
是 但即使...
Yes, but even...
等等 我有主意了 这招也许能打败财政部
Wait a minute. I've got an idea. This could be a way to beat the Treasury.
您是说您会支持我?     你说得有理
You mean you'll support me? You've made your point.
值得一试 我甚至会看你的报告...再看一遍
We'll give it a try. I'll even read your report. Again!
这会非常有趣 十分感谢你
This could be very interesting. Thank you very much indeed.
但您会支持我吗?
But will you support me?
当然 但不会公开
Yeah, well, not publicly.
这会削弱我的分量 削弱我的说服力
It would undermine my position, undermine the argument
如果我一开始就支持的话
if I supported you from the start.
我必须显得中立 被论据所说服
I have to be seen as the impartial judge swayed by the force of the argument.
对 我明白
Yes, I see that.
但是私下里 我希望强力推进此事 强力推进
But off the record, I'd like to see this pushed very hard indeed.
希望你发表些演说 彼得 非常感谢你
Make some speeches on it. Peter, thank you very much indeed.
谢谢你的香烟纸...香烟报告
Thank you for your cigarette paper... your paper on cigarettes.
您是认真的吗 首相?     什么 伯纳?
Is this serious? What do you mean?
一贯做法是反对
It's always been the practice
大臣们做反吸烟演说 做了的话 不印发 不推广
to discourage anti-smoking speeches by ministers and not to distribute them.
我希望彼得的演说能印发 并推广 人人都要知道
Well, I want Peter's speeches distributed. I want everybody to know.
是 首相 您认为您能赢吗?
Yes, Prime Minister. Do you think you will win this one?
烟草商的游说非常有力
The tobacco lobby is very powerful.
有赢就有输 伯纳 这次我必输无疑
Well, some you win, some you lose, Bernard. This one I shall definitely lose.
那是为什么?
Then why?
如果你是财政部长 你会选择减税15亿
If you were the Treasury, would you rather do without ?.5 billion in tax cuts
还是失去40亿烟草税呢?
or ? billion in lost tobacco tax revenue?
当然是减税
The tax cuts. (PHONE RINGS)
就是 那就是我的目的 我一定会达成
Exactly. That's what I want and that's what I shall get.
是汉弗莱爵士 他能来谈谈吗?     好 当然
Can Sir Humphrey have a word? Of course.
好 请进
Yes, come in, please.
首相      汉弗莱
Prime Minister... Humphrey.
我在想 您和索恩博士聊得高兴吗?
Did you have an interesting chat with Dr Thorne?
对 他提议彻底禁烟
Yes. He proposed the elimination of smoking.
也许要通过大规模催眠吧
By a campaign of mass hypnosis perhaps!
不 通过大幅提高烟草税 同时禁止一切广告
By raising tobacco taxes sky high and simultaneously banning all advertising.
你不觉得他的出发点非常崇高吗?
I think his position is admirably moral.
也许崇高 但是蠢到极点
Moral perhaps, but extremely silly.
头脑健全的人都不会考虑这种提议
No man in his right mind could contemplate such a proposal.
我就在考虑呢
I'm contemplating it.
是 当然 首相 请别误会
Yes, of course, Prime Minister. Please don't misunderstand me.
您当然要考虑您政府的所有行政提案
It is quite right that you should CONTEMPLATE all proposals
但没有正常人会支持它
but no sane man would ever SUPPORT it.
我就支持     这也是您应该的 首相
I'm supporting it. And quite right too, Prime Minister.
但问题是 烟草税是政府税收主要来源
The only problem is that the tax is a major source of revenue for the government.
也是致命疾病的主要来源
And a major source of death from diseases.
是 但并没有任何已证实的必然联系啊
Yes, but no definite causative link has ever been proved, has it?
但数据...     数据能证明任何事
The statistics... You can prove anything with statistics.
甚至事实?      对...不
Even the truth. Yes... No!
它说 "吸烟引起的疾病每年花费卫生部1.65亿"
It says here, ''Smoking-related diseases cost the NHS ?65 million a year.''
是 但我们调查过
Yes, but we've been into that.
结果是 如果这10万人活下来 寿终正寝
It has been shown that if those extra 100,000 people had lived to a ripe old age,
他们需要的养老金和社会保障金
they would have cost us even more in pensions and social security
比医疗费还要多
than they did in medical treatment.
所以从财政角度说 毫无疑问
So financially speaking, it's unquestionably better
保持现有的死亡率再好不过了
that they continue to die at about the present rate.
1833年 霍乱造成3万人死亡
''When cholera killed 30,000 people in 1833,
我们得到公共卫生法案
we got the Public Health Act.
1952年 工业废气造成2500人死亡
''When smog killed 2,500 people in 1952,
我们得到空气净化法案
we got the Clean Air Act.''
一种商业药物造成6人死亡
A commercial drug kills half a dozen people
我们禁止它出售
and we get it withdrawn from sale.
香烟每年杀死10万人 我们得到什么?
Cigarettes kill 100,000 people a year and what do we get?
40亿岁入
? billion a year.
25000个烟草业工作岗位 出口业蓬勃发展
25,000 jobs in the tobacco industry, a flourishing cigarette export business,
有效平衡了贸易额
helping our balance of trade,
25000个岗位涵盖零售 包装 贸易诸多领域
250,000 jobs related to tobacco newsagents, packaging, transport...
这些数据只是估计而已
These figures are just guesses.
不 这是政府数...是事实
No, they're government st... They're facts.
好 你的数据是事实 而我的事实只是数据?
So your statistics are facts and my facts are merely statistics?
首相 我站在您这边
I'm on your side.
我只是指出一些您会碰到的争论
I'm merely giving you some arguments you'll encounter.
谢谢 汉弗莱 真高兴连你都支持
Humphrey, I'm so glad to know we'll have support such as yours.
可首相 会有人指出
It will be pointed out that the
烟草公司是体育的重要赞助商
tobacco companies are great sponsors of sport.
一旦BBC的体育直播节目没有烟草广告...
Where would the BBC sports programmes be if cigarette companies couldn't advert...
没有烟草公司赞助 会怎样呢?
couldn't SPONSOR the events that they televise?
汉弗莱 我们在讨论每年10万人的死亡
We're talking about 100,000 deaths a year.
对 但烟草税占了公共卫生资金的1/3
Yes, but cigarette taxes pay for a third of the cost of the National Health Service.
我们多挽救了这么多生命
We're saving many more lives than we otherwise could
因为这些烟民自愿
because of those smokers who voluntarily
为挽救同胞们牺牲了自己
lay down their lives for their friends.
烟民是我们国家的恩人啊
Smokers are national benefactors.
只要他们活着
So long as they live!
吸烟和死亡的关系从未被证实 我说过了
Not that any definite causal link has ever been proved.
首相 内阁会议要开始了
It's time for your next Cabinet committee,
午餐安排在下院 体育大臣有急事找您
then the Minister of Sport wants an urgent word.
关于什么?      赞助
What about? Sponsorship.
谁向他告的密?他是烟草业的说客
Who tipped him off? He's one of the tobacco lobby.
是您政府中的一员
A member of YOUR government?
对 他是体育大臣 有既得利益
Yes, he's Minister for Sport. He has a vested interest.
还是诺丁汉的议员
He's also an MP for Nottingham.
你告诉他的? 他怎么会知道?
Did you tell him? How did he know?
小道消息 首相
The grapevine perhaps. Prime Minister...
告诉他 我2点半在下院见他10分钟
Tell the minister I'll see him at 2.30.
好的 首相      不好 伯纳 不过我是逃不掉了
With pleasure, Prime Minister. Not with pleasure, but I'll see him anyway.
首相 体育大臣来了
The Minister for Sport, Prime Minister.
莱斯利 亲爱的朋友 你好
Oh, Leslie, my dear fellow. Hi.
您介意我抽烟吗?
Do you mind if I smoke?
首相 有个流言
Prime Minister, it's about the rumour
说您本人打算攻击烟草业
that you intend to make a personal attack on the tobacco industry.
我没听说啊      您是说是假的?
I hadn't heard that rumour. It's not true?
卫生部大臣正有此意 但没人打算付诸实践
The Minister for Health is considering the matter.
无火不起烟
There's no smoke without fire.
会和你商议的 作为体育大臣 你有即得利益
You'd be consulted. As Minister for Sport, you have an interest.
别提什么体育
Never mind sport.
我有边缘选区在布里斯托尔 诺丁汉
There are marginal seats in Bristol, Nottingham,
格拉斯哥 巴塞尔顿和北爱尔兰
Glasgow, Basildon and Northern Ireland,
都是烟草工人的票
all with tobacco workers.
我选区里有4千烟草工人 我的席位怎么办?
I've got 4,000 tobacco workers in my constituency. What about my seat?
你的肺怎样?
What about your lungs?
我的肺好得很
My lungs are fine.
他不是用屁股(席位)来呼吸的
He doesn't breathe through his seat.
哦 席位 我懂了 抱歉
Oh, your seat, I see, I'm sorry.
谢谢 伯纳 我知道你的难处
Thank you, Bernard. I see the difficulty,
但只要符合国家利益
but if something is right for the country,
无疑 政府必须去做
surely the government must pursue it.
政府当然得做正确的事 只要不影响边缘选区
The government must do what's right, but not if it affects marginal constituencies.
这得有个限度      目前还没有下决定
There is a limit. No decision has been taken.
为了我们党的利益 你也不能这么做
For the good of the party, you can't do this.
你不是英国烟草集团聘的顾问吗?
Weren't you a paid consultant to the British Tobacco Group?
当然 英国烟草集团是给过我一丁点聘金
Of course, the fact that the BTG did pay me a small retainer,
这完全跑题了嘛
it's totally beside the point.
他们是非常慷慨的组织 有强烈的社会责任感
They're a very generous corporation with a strong sense of responsibility
看看他们给体育的钱吧 您还想制止他们
Look at all the money they give to sport!
他们只是为了卖出更多的烟
They just do it to sell more cigarettes.
不 他们把这当作是对社会的服务
No, they do it as a service to the community.
哦 好 他们喜欢捐款就匿名捐吧
Oh, that's all right, then. They can go on giving the money anonymously if they like.
我肯定他们会非常乐意
Well, I'm sure they'd be happy to,
如果他们能把匿名捐款的事迹公布的话
provided they could publicise the fact that they were doing it anonymously.
告诉我 彼得索恩是不是还想
Is it true that Peter Thorne is also trying to
改掉政府的健康警告?
change the government health warning?
是吗?
Is it?
貌似他提议改成"死于肺癌严重影响健康"
He's proposing something like ''Dying of lung cancer can seriously damage your health''.
这是撒谎
It is not true!
如果我们袖手旁观 在未来10年内
If we do nothing, in the next ten years,
我们一个国家 就会有100万人英年早逝
in this country we'll have one million premature deaths.
是 但却分布均匀
Yes, but evenly spread.
不局限在边缘选区里
Not just in marginal constituencies.
听着 吉姆 还没有任何有效证据表明
Listen, Jim, there is no conclusive proof of any causal link
是吸烟导致了...
between smoking and...
我们卫生部真的非常关心吸烟问题
We at the DHSS are profoundly worried about smoking.
我们的确有责任帮首相达成目标
And we agree it's our duty to help the Prime Minister achieve his objective,
但鉴于1/3选民都吸烟
but with a third of the voters as smokers,
我也不能把税抬得太高
I can't raise taxes too high.
一来 大臣不会在选票上自寻死路
The Chancellor won't commit electoral suicide
二来 通货膨胀也要考虑
and the inflationary effect is considerable.
但得承认 这事关道德原则
There is a moral principle involved.
道德原则 对
Moral principle, yes.
我们理解并支持首相的担心
We understand the PM's concern.
事实上 我们也相信道德原则
In fact, we earnestly believe in the moral principle.
但当关系到40亿税收
But where ? billion of revenue is at stake,
我想我们得极其慎重地考虑
I think we should have to consider very carefully
我们是否有权纵容自己
whether we have the right to indulge ourselves
自私地一味满足对道德的追求
in the rather selfish luxury of pursuing moral principles.
没有烟草商赞助 艺术怎么办呢?
Where would the arts be without tobacco sponsorship?
不是得靠艺术委员会了
At the mercy of the Arts Council.
可不是 那些愚蠢的压力集团
Exactly. Then those silly pressure groups and
狂热分子 像皇家内科医师协会
fanatics like the Royal College of Physicians!
狂热分子
Fanatics!
竟然奢想政府出台干预政策
They want the government to have a policy on the matter.
如果政府是一支团队 情况会不同
It would be different if the government were a team,
可惜实际上 它是敌对部落结成松散联邦体
but in fact they're a loose confederation of warring tribes.
要是首相见过烟草商
If only the PM could meet the tobacco people,
就会知道 他们都是多好的人啊
he could see what really nice chaps they were.
而且非常关心人民健康问题
And genuinely concerned about the health risks.
他们不可能有什么不对
There can't be anything wrong with them.
烟草集团理事会还有一位前常任秘书呢
BTG have an ex-Permanent Secretary on their board.
还能接纳更多      时机成熟的时候
And could well have more. In the fullness of time.
我觉得问题出在你们大臣本身 伊安
I think we ought to raise some questions about your minister, Ian.
对这个问题他懂什么? 索恩只是个医生
What does he know about the subject? Peter Thorne is only a doctor.
他唯一的目的就是让人活着
His sole purpose is keeping people alive!
偏见太重
Must be biased.
看到自己的病人死去
Seeing your patients die
一定从情绪上影响他的判断力
must emotionally distort your judgement.
完全可以理解 但感情用事是决策的大忌
It's very understandable, but a great handicap to cool decision-taking.
太对了 但找不出更有力的说辞吗?
Very true, but can we find something a bit stronger?
弗兰克 我想关键在于 我们生活在自由国家
Frank, I think the crucial argument is that we're living in a free country.
我们必须有权为自己作主
We must be free to make our own decisions.
不能把政府当保姆 我们可不想要个奶妈政府
Government shouldn't be a nursemaid. We don't want the nanny state.
好      好极了
Very good. Excellent.
唯一的问题是 这个说法
The only problem is that is also the argument
也被用来宣传大麻 海洛因 砒霜
for legalising the sale of marijuana, heroin
和硝化甘油合法化
arsenic and gelignite.
也许为它们课重税 也不失为一个好主意
Maybe that's a good idea if we put a big enough tax on them.
从政治上讲很难      太可惜了
Politically difficult. Pity.
是啊
Yes.
有了
Got it!
首相当年还是行政大臣的时候
When the Prime Minister was Minister for Administrative Affairs,
我常拉他去上院 温布尔登和格林徳堡歌剧院
I used to get him to accompany me on regular visits to Wimbledon Glyndebourne
去做烟草协会的贵宾
as a guest of BTG,
他可受了烟草商盛情款待 招待费少说上百
so he's thoroughly implicated in receiving hospitality worth hundreds,
甚至上千
possibly thousands from them.
如果把这消息漏出去 会多么轰动
Now, if that were to leak... shocking though a leak would be...
哦 是够轰动的      轰动
Oh, shocking. Shocking.
首相的处境一定会非常尴尬
It'd be profoundly embarrassing for the Prime Minister.
真搞不懂我怎么没早想到呢
I can't think why I didn't think of it before.
我也搞不懂
Nor can I.
好啊 伯纳      是 首相
Well, Bernard. Well, Prime Minister.
很好 伯纳 事情进展非常顺利
Very well. Things are going very well indeed.
好事啊
Oh, good.
我让财政部走投无路了 还有财政大臣
I've got the Treasury on the run and the Chancellor.
这好吗? 他可是您政府的一员
Is that good? He's in your own government.
当然好 他们得学会听话 跟我合作
Of course it's good. They've got to learn to come to heel and learn to co-operate.
您的"合作"怎么讲?      就是服从我的命令
What do you mean, co-operate? I mean obey my commands!
我懂了
I see.
"合作"就这个意思 当你是首相的时候
That's what ''co-operate'' means when you're Prime Minister.
首相 您为什么非要减税呢?
Why are these tax cuts in your interest?
我知道财政部不愿还钱 但他们也是您的政府
It's your government too.
伯纳 很简单 减税15亿能赢得大量选票
Bernard, it's simple. Cutting taxes by ?.5 billion is going to win us masses of votes.
我的大臣揽钱只为了自己的部门
My ministers are interested in getting money for their departments
而不是支持我
not in supporting me.
所以我要支持索恩 来和财政部抗衡
I'm using my support for Peter Thorne as leverage on the Treasury.
您的忠诚支持?      没错
Your loyal support? Precisely.
为了换他们的忠诚支持
In order to get THEIR loyal support.
等您达成减税 是不是要收回
After you get the tax cut, you will withdraw your
这一忠诚支持呢?
support from Peter Thorne?
伯纳 你怎么这么世故?
Bernard, how can you be so cynical?
我只调整一下优先级而已
I shall simply rearrange my priorities.
汉弗莱爵士在门外等候
Sir Humphrey's waiting to see you outside.
马上让他进来
Send him in at once.
是 首相 您的话就是我的"合作"
Yes, Prime Minister. Your word is my co-operation.
汉弗莱      首相大人
Humphrey! Prime Minister.
一切都还顺利吧?
Everything all right?
所有事 首相 恐怕都非常不顺利
Everything is very far from all right.
出什么问题了?      您的禁烟法令
What's the trouble? Your anti-smoking legislation.
怎么了?
What about it?
尽管您的提议
Notwithstanding the fact that your proposal
能够带来一些无关紧要的附加利益
could encompass certain concomitant benefits of a peripheral relevance,
但同时恐怕会造成极其重大之至的顾虑
there is a countervailing consideration of infinitely superior magnitude,
甚至牵扯到您的自律与渎职行为
involving your personal complicity and corroborative malfeasance,
后果是 您从前的交情与娱乐活动的漏洞和污点
with the consequence that the taint and stigma of your former diversions
将无可救药地 不可避免地动摇您的位置
could irredeemably and irretrievably invalidate your position
并在公众揭发和舆论谴责下 让您难堪到极点
and culminate in public revelations and recriminations of a profoundly embarrassing
最终毫无挽回余地
and ultimately indefensible character.
也许你该对这番话做个总结
Perhaps I could have a pr閏is of that.
您双手沾满尼古丁      这作何理解?
There's nicotine on your hands. What do you mean?
烟草协会给我们的所有那些好处
All the hospitality that we've enjoyed at BTG's expense.
香槟招待会 午餐会
Champagne receptions,
体育比赛和文艺演出的贵宾席
the best seats at sporting and cultural events.
有什么问题?      烟草公司可能
What's the problem?
把这些难堪事告诉媒体
The tobacco companies may tell the press.
难堪什么? 我在苏联大使馆喝过酒
So? I've had drinks at the Soviet embassy.
也不能就说我是俄国间谍吧
That doesn't make me a Russian spy.
哦...好...哦
Oh... Well... Oh.
是不是?      好 好
Does it? Well, no.
随他们去捣鬼吧 还有别的吗?
Let them do their worst. Anything else?
首相 还有非常重要的一点您要切记
Well, Prime Minister, there is another vital point to bear in mind.
许多人 赫赫有名的人物 有影响的人物
A lot of eminent people, influential people
都争论说 这种法令是对自由选择权的侵犯
argue that such legislation would be a blow against freedom of choice.
一派胡言 我又没禁止吸烟本身
Rubbish! I'm not banning smoking
难道每次加税就是对自由的剥夺?
Does every tax rise represent a blow against freedom?
这要取决于税加了多少
Well, it depends how big the tax rise is.
好极了 20便士算剥夺自由了吗?
Fascinating! Does 20 pence represent a blow against freedom?
首相      25? 30便士? 31?
Prime Minister... 25 pence? 30 pence? 31?
只要严重损害你利益 就是破坏自由吗?
Is something a blow against freedom because it can seriously damage your wealth?
首相 我得警告您会有阻碍
I must warn you of the difficulties.
我预见到种种不可预见的问题
I foresee all sorts of unforeseen problems.
比如?
Such as?
如果我能预见 那还叫不可预见的问题吗?
If I could foresee them, they wouldn't be unforeseen.
但你刚刚说你可以预见啊
You just said you COULD foresee them.
首相 如果发起部际委员会 议会调查
If we could set up an inter-departmental committee,
皇家调查委员会 或者财政部调查组
a Royal Commission, perhaps a Treasury Committee...
别和我谈财政部      为什么?
Don't talk to me about the Treasury! Why not?
他们为了15亿 就企图阻止我的减税计划
The Treasury are blocking my plans for a ?.5 billion tax cut.
要是他们能...灵活些
If only they could be more...flexible.
我觉得 他们还没认真研究过这事
Well, I don't think they're fully committed on that other matter yet.
是吗?
Really?
当然没有 灵活? 我肯定他们能找到办法
Absolutely not. Oh, no, I'm sure they could find a way.
他们行吗?
Could they?
唯一的绊脚石 就是您的禁烟令一旦通过
The only stumbling block would be if your anti-smoking proposals went through,
他们减了这个 别的地方就减不了了
they'd be too busy with those to find a way to help with the other cuts.
当然 我的禁烟令本身很重要
Well, of course, my anti-smoking proposals, important though they are,
但在国防面前 恐怕就微不足道了
don't have nearly such a high priority as defence.
卫生大臣来了首相
The Minister of State for Health is here.
首相 请允许我去打几个电话 多谢
Prime Minister, if I might have one or two minutes to make some phone calls. Thank you.
带他进来 伯纳
Show him in, Bernard.
索恩博士      彼得 我能为你做什么?
Dr Thorne. Peter, what can I do for you?
我得到些激动人心的消息
I've just had some very exciting news.
我们得到了英国医学会 皇家内科学会
We've got full backing from the BMA
和8个顶级医学院校的全力支持
and eight top scientific and medical colleges.
棒极了
Marvellous.
但你的法案不可能马上通过
But your legislation can't be put through immediately.
当然 但在3个月内要宣布为政府政策
It is announced as government policy within three months
一年内发布白皮书 时间挺充裕的
And a white paper in 1 year
是 说到这 我遇到了一些困难 财政部 你知道的
Yes, since we spoke, I've encountered a few problems. The Treasury, you know.
还有您没预料到的吗?      对 我是说不...是的
Can't be anything you didn't know already? Yes. I mean no... Well, yes.
彼得 这不是你想象的那么简单
Peter, it's not as simple as you think.
吉姆 我真的非常重视这个
Jim, I really am serious about this.
这是唯一一件我政治生涯中能做到的
It's the one really important and worthwhile thing
重要的 值得的事情
I believe I can do in politics.
如果你阻碍它 我只有辞职 并公布原因
If you stall it, I'll have to resign. And say why.
对不起 首相 汉弗莱爵士有急事找您
Excuse me, Prime Minister. Could Sir Humphrey see you urgently just for a moment?
你能在外面等等吗 彼得?      好的
Would you mind waiting outside, Peter? Of course.
首相 事情非常顺利
Prime Minister, it's quite all right.
财政部再度审阅了您的提案
The Treasury have looked at your proposal again
他们同意减税了
and they can encompass your tax cut,
但前提是禁烟令到此为止
provided no work is needed on the anti-smoking proposal.
好 汉弗莱 但我又有麻烦了
That's fine, but there is another complication.
彼得索恩说我取消禁烟 他就辞职
Peter Thorne is going to resign if I drop it,
向媒体告状 让我被全国医生和科学家谴责
go to the press and have me condemned by all the doctors and scientists in Britain.
救命啊
Help!
您在财政部不是还有一个空位吗?
You still have that government vacancy in the Treasury?
你是说...这可是破格提拔 连升三级
You mean...? It's a very big promotion, a very rapid one.
算不了什么 对这么能干的大臣来说
Nevertheless, for a very able minister.
伯纳 让彼得进来 然后把环境大臣叫来
Bernard, get Peter back in here and then get on to the Department of the Environment.
体育大臣还在的话 一起叫来
Get Leslie Potts over here at once.
首相 我还是先...您别介意
Prime Minister, I think I'll just, erm... If you'll excuse me.
索恩博士
Dr Thorne.
彼得 我刚想到 我们在财政部还有个空位
Peter, I've just remembered we still have that vacancy at the Treasury.
我绞尽脑汁想找人填补
I've been racking my brains how to fill it,
而你这份报告 我得说 让人过目难忘
but your work on this paper has impressed me enormously.
你不是想打发掉我吧?
You're not trying to get rid of me?
当然不是 恰恰相反
Definitely not. Quite the reverse.
这可是大提拔啊
It's a terrific step up.
你应得的 你完全能胜任
But thoroughly merited.
如果要放弃禁烟案的话 我怎能接受呢?
How can I take it if it means dropping my bill?
彼得 坐下
Peter, sit down.
我跟你开诚布公地说
Let me be absolutely honest with you.
这项法案可能...肯定会很难通过
This legislation would have been...would be... will be very difficult to get through.
财政部是最大的障碍 而不是卫生部
The Treasury is the stumbling block, not the Department of Health.
会花很久 但如果你深入内部 弄清内幕
It'll take longer, but if you were inside learning the ropes,
我们会有更大可能
we'd have a much better chance of
制订一项万无一失的法案 载入史册
a watertight, foolproof Act when it gets to the statute book.
相信我      这么说我提案没被撤销?
Believe me. So my proposals aren't dropped?
当然没有
Absolutely not.
好 那我接受财政部的差事      好极了
OK. I'll take the Treasury job. Good.
太感谢了 再见 首相
Thanks a lot. Goodbye, Prime Minister.
这下卫生部又有个空位了 现在...
That leaves us with a vacancy at the Department of Health. Now...
体育大臣来了 首相
The Minister for Sport is here, Prime Minister.
进来      帕兹先生
Come in. Mr Potts!
莱斯利 我亲爱的朋友
Leslie! My dear chap.
请坐 好
Sit down. Now...
由你来做卫生大臣 你意下如何?
How would you like to be Minister of Health?
我?      是的
Me? Yes.
这个...
Well...
这可是个大提拔啊
It's a considerable promotion.
你应得的 你完全能胜任
But thoroughly merited.
你非常适合这份工作
You're very suitable for the job.
你可不是那种医学说客 不像索恩博士
You're not one of the medical lobby like Dr Peter Thorne.
好 那我恭敬不如从命 谢谢 首相
Well, of course I can't refuse it. Thank you, Prime Minister.
汉弗莱 见见我们新任卫生大臣
Humphrey, meet our new Minister for Health.
哦 恭喜恭喜
Oh, congratulations.
但如果要和烟草业对着干 我坚决拒绝
I don't want the job if it means attacking the tobacco industry.
绝对不会
Ah, but it wouldn't.
你看 莱斯利 我们政府官员必须得现实
You see, Leslie, we in government have to be realists.
我希望你配合烟草业工作
I want you to work WITH the tobacco industry.
他们真的很想解决问题
They're only trying to sort out the problems.
他们有很多资源 人也不错
They've got huge resources, nice chaps,
很人道主义 职员素质也高
caring people and really fabulous employers.
他们真的在出力
They are really trying to help.
我希望你和他们一起干 而不是对着干
I want you to work with the industry, not against it.
好不好?
All right?
他说什么?
What did he say?
我想他在说 "是 首相"
I think he said, ''Yes, Prime Minister.''
破烂熊字幕组 -==www.RagBear.com==- 欢迎加入